<section id="secControls">
	<title>Controls</title>

	<indexterm><primary>chart control</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraChartControl">
		<title>Chart Control</title>
		<para>This control can render historic data, as a time series graph, or current
      values as a comparative bar chart. Various display styles are available.</para>

      <para>When creating a custom chart view use the &lt;renderer&gt; tag to specify
      display options:</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">
    &lt;renderer type=""&gt;
        &lt;domain id=""/&gt;
        &lt;range id=""/&gt;
        &lt;range id=""/&gt;
        ...
    &lt;/renderer&gt;
		</programlisting>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>&lt;renderer&gt;(mandatory): multiple renderers can be specified, as
         long as all of them belong to the same class (either Category or XY), as detailed
         below.</listitem>
			<listitem>type(mandatory): one of the following values:</listitem>
		      <itemizedlist>

			   <indexterm><primary>XY renderers</primary></indexterm>
               <listitem>XY class renderers: display continuous information along the X
               axis, most common example is a time series chart.
		            <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>XYLine: shows a horizontal continuous line for each of
                     the ranges. </listitem>
                     <listitem>XYArea: same as XYLine, but the area below the line is filled.
                     Multiple ranges will be shown overlapped, and will be better
                     visible by setting opacity level to less than 100%.</listitem>
                     <listitem>StackedXYArea: same as XYArea, but multiple ranges
                     will be shown stacked one on top of the other.</listitem>
		            </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>

			   <indexterm><primary>Category renderers</primary></indexterm>
               <listitem>Category class renderers: display information grouped by discrete
               values on the X axis, for example bar charts.
		            <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>Bar2D: shows 2D vertical bars of different colors for each range.
                     Multiple ranges are shown as bars close together.</listitem>
                     <listitem>StackedBar2D: same as Bar2D, but multiple ranges are shown as
                     bars stacked one on top of the other.</listitem>
                     <listitem>Bar3D: same as Bar2D, but with a depth effect which makes it
                     easier to identify zero values.</listitem>
                     <listitem>StackedBar3D: same as StackedBar2D but with a depth effect.</listitem>
                     <listitem>CategoryLine: the discrete values of the domain axis are
                     joined by a continuous line.</listitem>
                     <listitem>CategoryArea: same as CategoryLine, but the area under the line
                     is filled. Multiple ranges will be shown overlapped, and will be better
                     visible by setting opacity level to less than 100%.</listitem>
                     <listitem>CategoryStackedArea: same as CategoryArea, but multiple ranges
                     will be shown stacked one on top of the other. </listitem>
		            </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>

		      </itemizedlist>
            <listitem>&lt;domain&gt;(mandatory): identifies the resource to be used as a
            generator for values on the X axis.</listitem>

            <listitem>&lt;range&gt;(mandatory): identifies the resource to be used as a
            generator for values on the Y axis. Multiple &lt;range&gt; tags are allowed</listitem>

            <listitem>id: must be a valid identifier of one of the results (Function or Resource)
            provided by the Query.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<figure>
			<title>Category Chart Controls: Bar2D, StackedBar2D, Bar3D, StackedBar3D,
         CategoryLine, CategoryArea, CategoryStackedArea</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/chart_control_category.png"/>
		</figure>
		<figure>
			<title>XY Chart Controls: XYLine, XYArea, StackedXYArea</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/chart_control_xy.png"/>
		</figure>

      <para>When plotting numeric raw counters &programName; will create a chart of type
      XYLine, with the timestamp as the domain and the counters as ranges.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>Table control</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraTableControl">
		<title>Table Control</title>
		<para>This control displays the raw results of the query in a tabular format,
      allowing sorting, filtering and dynamic chart creation with selected values. It is
      especially useful for queries based on regular expressions.</para>

      <para>When creating custom views, a table control will by default include all results
      of the Query as columns in the table. However you must also use the following tags.</para>

		<programlisting role="linespecific">
   &lt;category id=""/&gt;
   &lt;column id=""/&gt;
   &lt;column id=""/&gt;
   ...
		</programlisting>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>&lt;category&gt;(mandatory): selects one resource as the category, used
         when creating bar charts from values in the table.
         This tag can only have one optional attribute: &lt;removeStale&gt; that has a boolean value. If the value is
         true than after every data collection cycle all items that have not been updated will be removed from the table.
         The default value of this attribute is false.
         </listitem>

         <listitem>&lt;column&gt;(optional): if no &lt;column&gt; tag is specified, all results
         of the Query will be included in the table. Otherwise the table will only contain
         resources specified by &lt;category&gt; and &lt;column&gt; tags.</listitem>

         <listitem>id: must be a valid identifier of one of the results (Function or Resource)
         provided by the Query.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<figure>
			<title>Table Control</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/table_control.png"/>
		</figure>


      <para>The control will color table cells with shades of red or green, to show that
      the values have been increasing or decreasing, respectively.</para>

      <para>The filter option allows you to quickly reduce the volume of information to
      only a relevant subset.The type of filter for a column depends on the type of values
      in that column:

		<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>String
		<figure>
			<title>String filter</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/filter_string.png"/>
		</figure>
		<para>Check the 'Negative match' box if you want to keep just items that do not match the filter.</para>
		</listitem>

        <listitem>Number
		<figure>
			<title>Number filter</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/filter_number.png"/>
		</figure>
		</listitem>

         <listitem>Date
		<figure>
			<title>Date filter</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/filter_date.png"/>
		</figure>
		</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>

      </para>

      <para>Dynamic charts can be created, having table's category as domain, and selected
      columns as ranges. See <xref linkend="paraChartControl"/> for a list of chart styles.
      The control will prompt you to select the renderer type, and which columns to show.
      </para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Plot contents as bar charts. This will prompt you to select a Category
         class chart renderer. All values shown in the table will be displayed as a bar chart.
         Note that if a filter is applied only the visible items are included.</listitem>

         <listitem>Plot contents as time series. This will prompt you to select a XY
         class chart renderer. All values except the category will be shown in a time series
         (history) chart. Note that if a filter is applied only the visible items are included.</listitem>

         <listitem>Plot selected as bar charts. Creates a bar chart, but only includes
         selected items.</listitem>

         <listitem>Plot selected as time series. Creates a time series chart, but only
         includes selected items.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	</sect2>

    <indexterm><primary>Properties control</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraPropertiesControl">
		<title>Properties Control</title>
		<para>Simple control which shows query results as a list of name / value pairs.</para>

      <para>When creating custom views there are no additional tags required for this control.
      All query results will be included in the output.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Properties Control</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/properties_control.png"/>
		</figure>
	</sect2>

    <indexterm><primary>Log record viewer</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraLogRecordViewer">
		<title>Log Record Viewer</title>
		<para>This is a specialized control used only to visualize application log records.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Log Record Viewer</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/log_board.png"/>
		</figure>

	</sect2>
	<para></para>
	<para></para>

</section>
