<section id="secConcepts">
	<title>Concepts</title>

	<indexterm><primary>concepts</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraOverview">
		<para>&programName; is a performance and resource monitoring tool, designed to present
		heterogenous data collected from various sources in a graphical way. In &programName;
		data is collected by Agents and passed to the Console to be displayed
		visually, or to be recorded for later playback.</para>

		<para>There are two main modes of monitoring using &programName; and choosing one
		over the other depends whether Host Manager can or needs to be installed on the target machine.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Agent based monitoring</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/agent_based_monitoring.gif"/>
		</figure>
		<para>Agent based monitoring means that the Host Manager component is running on the monitored host
		and agents are deployed in 'Remote' mode. Use this method only if necessary as it usually consumes more
		resources on the monitored system.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Agentless monitoring</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/agentless_monitoring.gif"/>
		</figure>
		<para>This is the preferred way to monitor a system as it usually is more efficient.
		Depending on the platform and the type of application being sampled,
		some application-specific client tools may be required; an example would be DB2 and Websphere.
		Others will only require configuring permissions to allow remote access, as is the case
		when retrieving Windows information through the Remote Registry service. Process-based
		providers may also be created to execute command line tools through the rexec utility or via
		telnet or ssh2 sessions.</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>agents</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraAgents">
		<title>Agents</title>
		<para>Agents have the responsibility of collecting data from various sources and
		making it available to the Console. Depending on the type of application or system
		being monitored, an agent can perform its data-collecting duties in two modes:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>local: the agent itself is run locally and collects data through the
			network from the monitored system.</listitem>
			<listitem>remote: Host Manager must have been installed on the monitored system.
			The agent will run on the remote host and will use Host Monitor to send data
			to the Console.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>providers</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraProviders">
		<title>Providers</title>
		<para>Providers are extensions or building blocks for custom monitoring. Their role is to collect
		small pieces of data in a very simple form and send it to the Console where it will be parsed and
		inserted into a hierarchical structure.
		<para>There are three types of providers that can be built:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Process: the monitoring data is extracted using external processes.</listitem>
			<listitem>SQL: the monitoring data is extracted using a database connection and SQL statements.</listitem>
			<listitem>Java: the monitoring data is extracted using custom Java code.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>host manager</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraHostManager">
		<title>Host Manager</title>
		<para>A Host Manager provides an environment for agents to run in, and acts as a
		gateway to the Console.</para>

		<para>Install the Host Manger on a monitored machine only if you cannot run the agent in
		'Local' mode(this usually happens when client side libraries are required but not
		available on the Console but note that some agents like the 'Log File Monitor' will always
		require a Host Manger to be running on a remote host). </para>

		<para>Even without any agent enabled a Host Manager will provide a few information
		elements about the host it runs on. This information (operating system version, architecture
		and time difference between the host and Console) can be seen by selecting the host node
		in the session tree.</para>

		<para>When started, Host Manager will detect all available network interfaces and will prompt
		you to select the one to use.</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>console</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraConsole">
		<title>Console</title>
		<para>All control and display functions of &programName; are available from the Console.
		Data from all hosts and all agents is presented in a hierarchical layout and can be displayed
		on screen, or can be recorded in a log file.</para>

		<para>Individual performance counters from each agent can be plotted on charts,
		tables, properties or dedicated viewers.
		More complex queries can also be defined, grouping multiple counters from
		different agents or different hosts on the same chart or table. A powerful syntax
		is provided for specifying counters to be plotted, described in more detail under <xref linkend="secCustomViews"/>.
		</para>

		<para>As described under <xref linkend="secCustomData"/>, user-defined agents and providers
		can also be created from the Console, and can be used along with the built-in agents.</para>

		<para>For ways to create rules that trigger alerts and various reactions see <xref linkend="secReactions"/>.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>monitoring session</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>session</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraMonitoringSession">
		<title>Monitoring Session</title>
		<para>In &programName; all information related to a monitoring sesion
		(hosts, activated agents, counters plotted and so on) can be saved together
		as a session file (*.lperf).</para>

		<para>When restoring a session &programName; will attempt to connect to the same
		hosts and enable the same agents, while restoring the screen layout with all
		charts visible at the time when the session was saved.</para>

		<para>Saving sessions is a convenient way to manage all your lists of hosts and
		configuration (such as database connection parameters etc) for each one.</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>sampling interval</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraSamplingInterval">
		<title>Sampling Interval</title>
		<para>Data will be collected regularly from agents, with a
		frequency controlled by the Sampling Interval parameter.</para>

		<para>The Sampling Interval is typically adjusted at Monitoring Session level
		by changing the value on the application toolbar. This value is propagated
		and used by all agents, unless overriden.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Setting Sampling Interval at Session level</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/toolbar_sample_interval.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>This setting can be overriden at an agent level by unselecting the 'Default' interval
		checkbox. More complex agents also allow adjusting the sampling interval per entity.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Setting Sampling Interval at Agent Level</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/agent_interval.png"/>
		</figure>

	<indexterm><primary>entity refresh schedule</primary></indexterm>
	<para>
		You can also configure an entity to update its children periodically. Right click on the entity and from the 
		context menu choose 'Refresh Schedule'. Note that this action might not be available on
		every entity. In the dialog box enter a value which will represent the number of
		sampling intervals between entity update operations. </para>

		<figure>
			<title>Setting Entity Refresh Schedule</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/entity_refresh_period.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>
		Once a refresh schedule was set for an entity a refresh icon will upear next to it like in the
		following example:
		</para>
		
		<figure>
			<title>Entity Refresh Schedule Icon</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/entity_refresh_period_icon.png"/>
		</figure>
		
		<para>
		Note that certain entities are not able to refresh their children and in such circumstances
		the schedule is set on the first ancestor entity or agent able to refreh its descendants. In this case 
		a refresh icon will be shown for both the original entity and its ancestor.
		</para>
		
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>monitoring level</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraMonitoringLevel">
		<title>Monitoring Level</title>
		<para>For certain agents (WebSphere) the monitoring level can be specified at agent or entity level.
		The monitoring level controls the amount and type of data that will be collected by the agent.
		By lowering the monitoring level you can reduce the impact of monitoring on the monitored system.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Setting monitoring level at entity level</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/monitoring_level.png"/>
		</figure>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>entity</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>counter</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraEntitiesCounters">
		<title>Entities and Counters</title>
		<para>In &programName; counters are the basic performance elements, and they have an
		associated value that can be for example plotted on a chart. Counters are
		typically grouped under entities, which in turn are grouped hierarchically under
		an agent.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Agent, Entities and Counters</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/entity_counter.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>In the figure above you can see entities of the Windows agent, as well
		as the counters for the selected entity (Processor)</para>

		<para>An agent will return data only for the counters which are enabled. To
		enable counters, click the checkbox next to them, then click 'Apply'. Enabling
		counters is also required for recording a session log: only data for enabled
		counters will be recorded. Note that when enabling a view or a dashboard
		(see <xref linkend="paraViewsDashboards"/>) all required counters are automatically enabled.
		This is also true for views which use regular expressions.</para>

		<para>Counters can also be enabled by right-clicking any entity of an agent
		and selecting 'Enable All Counters' or 'Enable All Counters Recursively'. The
		recursive option will also enable all counters of all child entities. Dynamic
		counters (created during a monitoring session) will be created enabled if their
		parent entity was enabled in this way.</para>

		<indexterm><primary>monitoring level</primary></indexterm>
		<para>Some agents support the concept of Monitoring Level associated with their
		entities and counters. This allows the user to control the volume of information
		displayed, with higher levels resulting in more entities and counters present
		in agent's tree. If this is supported, markers will be displayed next to each
		entity to show the current level. Options are provided to control monitoring
		level per each entity, per subtree or per entire agent.</para>
	</sect2>


	<indexterm><primary>view</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>dashboard</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraViewsDashboards">
		<title>Views and Dashboards</title>
		<para>A very powerful feature of &programName; is the ability to group related
		counters, together with graphic display hints, into a single View object, easy
		to plot with one click. A view can group counters from the same agent entity
		(eg: Disk Reads, Disk Writes for a PhysicalDisk entity), different entities as well as counters
		across multiple hosts (eg: Disk Reads for all monitored hosts).</para>

		<para>Along with Views there are also Dashboards, which are groups of views and
		individual counters that can be plotted together, making it easy to display all
		relevant performance metrics for an entire system</para>

		<para>Both views and dashboards can be found at any level in the monitoring
		session tree.</para>

		<para>Views and dashboards can also be customized or created from scratch, see
		<xref linkend="secCustomViews"/>.</para>

		<indexterm><primary>screen</primary></indexterm>
		<para>To control the volume of information shown at a time on the screen, more
		dashboards can be placed under a Data View Screen and shown or hidden
		together. &programName; creates an initial screen; more screens can be created
		later on using the tooolbar controls.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Data View Screen toolbar controls</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/dataview_screen.png"/>
		</figure>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>alerts</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>reactions</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>email</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraReactions">
		<title>Reactions and Alerts</title>
		<para>In &programName; it is possible to define complex rules for triggering reactions such as
		visual alerts, emails, jobs and advices. For more information see <xref linkend="secReactions"/> and
		<xref linkend="secJobs"/></para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>html web generation</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraHTMLGeneration">
		<title>HTML Generation</title>
		<para>In &programName; it is also possible to generate a HTML page with all the data
		available in the current monitoring session; the HTML generator can be set to refresh the generated data periodically.
		For more information see <xref linkend="secHTMLGeneration"/></para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>command line non-interactive</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraNonInteractive">
		<title>Non-Interactive Monitoring Session</title>
		<para>You can also start a monitoring session in a non-interactive manner using 
		
		<programlisting role="linespecific">
		batchStart.bat(sh) [sessionName] [logFile]
		</programlisting>
		
		where the two parameters are the monitoring session name
		and the log file where monitoring data will be stored.
		To stop a session started with batchStart you must run batchStop.bat(sh)</para>
	</sect2>

	<para></para>
	<para></para>

</section>
