<section id="secLogging">
	<title>Log and Replay</title>

	<indexterm><primary>logging</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraLogging">
		<title>Logging</title>

		<para>&programName; can record into an offline file all performance data
		collected during a monitoring session. This data can later be replayed
		in offline mode (without a connection to agents or Host Managers) for
		further analysis.</para>

		<para>Logging can be enabled at any point during a monitoring session by
		clicking the 'Data Logging' button on the toolbar. Incoming data will start
		being recorded in the selected log file. The current version of &programName; only
		supports logging to a disk file.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>log replay</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraReplaying">
		<title>Replaying</title>

		<para>To replay a logged session click the 'Load Log' toolbar button and
		select the log file. A dialog will open as in the figure bellow that prompts you to adjust the
		time interval to replay.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Log Replay Configuration Dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/log_replay_config.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>You can have even more control over the speed of the replay operation by
		adjusting the aggregation interval.
		The aggregation interval is specified in seconds; all samples collected during this
		interval will be averaged into one value. Increasing this value can speed up considerably
		the replay of large log files, although at the expense of some detail.</para>

		<para>Please note that some information (for intstance log file records) will never be aggregated no matter
		what the settings for the log replay.</para>

		<para>After loading a log file, the Console's user interface will change slightly to
		show the log playback controls.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Log Replay Controls</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/log_controls.png"/>
		</figure>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>1 - Starts/restarts the playing of the logged data</listitem>
			<listitem>2 - Pauses the playing of the logged data</listitem>
			<listitem>3 - Resets the playing of the logged data</listitem>
			<listitem>4 - This control is enabled only when the data being replayed is not aggregated; it controls
			the speed at which log records are replayed</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>In log playback mode the session tree is still available but with the
		following restrictions:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Hosts and agents cannot be edited.</listitem>
			<listitem>Only counters and entities which were enabled during recording
			are shown.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>

		<para>It is important to note that replaying a log does not limit your ability
		to plot different counters or to define custom views. All counters that were
		enabled during recording are now available for plotting, regardless whether
		they were plotted during the original monitoring session or not.</para>

	</sect2>
	<para></para>
	<para></para>

</section>
