<section id="secCustomViews">
	<title>Defining Custom Views</title>

	<para>A powerful feature of &programName; is the ability to define custom charts and
	tables based on multiple counters. As described below, defining a custom view has
	two parts: specifying data to plot through a Query and specifying rendering options
	(specific to each control).</para>

	<indexterm><primary>identifiers</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraResourceIdentifiers">
		<title>Identifiers</title>

		<para>It is important to note that names of entities and counters as displayed
		on screen are human-readable, localised names. These names don't always match
		the real identifier used underneath by the application, and which must be used
		when defining custom views. To reveal these identifiers select 'Toggle Identifiers'
		on the View menu.</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>query</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraQueries">
		<title>Queries</title>

		<para>The Query object is the part of the View definition that specifies what data
		needs to be collected and processed before being displayed. Resources, functions
		(see below) and reactions are defined together inside a Query. Syntax:</para>

		<programlisting role="linespecific">
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;resource id="" rid=""/&gt;
        ...
        &lt;function op="" id=""&gt;
            &lt;param id=""/&gt;
        &lt;/function&gt;
        ...
        &lt;reaction params=""...&gt;
        ...
        &lt;/reaction&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
		</programlisting>

		<para>Multiple &lt;resource&gt;, &lt;function&gt; and &lt;reaction&gt; tags can be specified. As
		described below, Functions act as virtual counters and generate values based on
		Resources defined in the same Query.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>view</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraViews">
		<title>Views</title>

		<para>Along with a Query to provide data, control-specific rendering options
		must be provided, to specify how data should be displayed on screen.</para>

		<para>Plotting a view always results in a control being created, and depending
		on the chosen control different options are available. See <xref linkend="secControls"/>
		for details.</para>

	</sect2>


	<indexterm><primary>resource</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraResources">
		<title>Resources</title>

		<para>In &programName;'s terminology a Resource is a fully specified entity or
		counter. A resource's syntax contains up to four parts separated by '/':</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">&lt;host&gt;/&lt;agent&gt;/&lt;entity&gt;/[&lt;counter&gt;]</programlisting>

		<para>Note that the counter part is always enclosed in square brackets; this is to
		unambiguosly separate it from the entity part. Here's an example:</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">localhost/windows/root/LogicalDisk/C:/[Disk Writes/sec]</programlisting>

		<para>The above resource identifies the 'Disk Writes/sec' counter of the
		'LogicalDisk/C:' entity of the 'Windows' agent on machine 'localhost'.</para>

		<para>Relative resource paths can also be used. Views can be created at different
		levels (host, agent or entity level) in the monitoring session tree. All views are
		aware of their location, and if host or agent names are not specified, the current
		values will be used. Rewriting the above example:</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">-/-/root/LogicalDisk/C:/[Disk Writes/sec]</programlisting>

		<para>Assuming this resource was saved under an entity of the Windows agent, when plotted
		it will dynamically complete the path with the real names of the host and agent it was
		plotted from. This allows the same query to be reused on different hosts, or on different
		agent instances.</para>

		<para>This is the XML syntax for specifying a resource:</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">&lt;resource id="" rid="" name="" description="" iname="" format="" type=""/&gt;</programlisting>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>id(mandatory): a short unique id to be used as reference in the same query (see below).</listitem>
			<listitem>rid(mandatory): resource identifier as described above.</listitem>
			<listitem>name(optional): text to be displayed as the name of this resource.</listitem>
			<listitem>description(optional): descriptive text for this resource.</listitem>
			<listitem>iname(optional): instance name (see regular expressions below) designed to have
			different values for each entity matched by a regular expression.</listitem>
			<listitem>type(optional): can be one of 'string', 'number' or 'date'. Used to
			determine data type for the value returned and to choose the appropriate rendering. It is used in general to
			override the native type of the counter(for instance to display a long value as a date).</listitem>
			<listitem>format(optional): format specifier used when displaying values provided by this resource
			(see <xref linkend="paraFormattingSyntax"/>).</listitem>
			<listitem>code(optional): Java code (body of a Java function) to be executed
         with this resource as an input parameter. This is a shorthand for creating a
         &lt;function op="script"&gt; tag (see <xref linkend="paraFunctionScript"/>).</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Both 'name' and 'iname' accept a series of tags which will be replaced at
		runtime with actual values. More information can be found under
		<xref linkend="paraResourceTags"/>.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>regular expressions</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraRegularExpressions">
		<title>Regular Expressions</title>

		<para>Each of the four components of a resource can be also specified as a regular
		expression (see <xref linkend="paraRESyntax"/>). To indicate that a resource
		component is to be treated as a regular expression, rather than a fixed string,
		enclose it in brackets. Example:</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">localhost/windows/root/LogicalDisk/(.*)/[Disk Writes/sec]</programlisting>

		<para>Note that a part of the entity component is enclosed in brackets, which means it is to
		be treated as a regular expression. This above example identifies all [Disk Writes/sec]
		counters for all logical disks on localhost.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>function</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraFunctions">
		<title>Functions</title>
		<para>Values returned by resources can be further processed by using Functions.
		A function can use the input of more Resources and will produce a value as result.
		This is the syntax for defining a function:</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">
    &lt;function op="" id="" name="" description="" iname="" format="" type=""&gt;
        &lt;param id=""/&gt;
        &lt;param id=""/&gt;
        ...
    &lt;/function&gt;
		</programlisting>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>id(mandatory): a short unique id to be used as reference in the same query (see below).</listitem>
			<listitem>op(mandatory): the operation this function performs (see <xref linkend="secFunctions"/>).</listitem>
			<listitem>name,description,iname,format,type(optional): same as Resource's
			attributes described above. If not specified the function will inherit them
			from the resources it uses.</listitem>
			<listitem>param(optional): if the function requires parameters a &lt;param&gt; tag must
			be used for each one, and the id attribute must specify one of the resources
			defined in the same query. Multiple &lt;param&gt; tags are allowed.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>See <xref linkend="secFunctions"/> for a list of functions supported by this
		version of &programName;.</para>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>view editor</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraViewEditor">
		<title>View Editor</title>

		<para>New views can be created with the use of the View Editor. To access this
		editor select View tab of an entity, right click and choose 'Add' from the
		context menu.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>View Editor</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/view_editor.png"/>
		</figure>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>view wizard</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraViewWizard">
		<title>View Wizard</title>

		<para>A view wizard is provided that makes easier the creation of some of the most common
		data view types:

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Homogeneous data view: this is a view that requires similar entities which will be selected
			using a regular expression. Used mainly to create views using one entity's children, for instance
			the processes running on a host or the SQL statements for a database... It is usually defined at the
			level of the parent entity but it can be defined anywhere in the monitoring session tree.</listitem>
			<listitem>Heterogeneous data view: this is a view that requires counters from entities which are
			not necessarily related such as the CPU, disks, memory... It can also be used to create views
			from the counters of the same entity. As an important note: in the current version it is
			necessary that all the entities involved in such a data view have the same source (agent or
			provider). This only applies for agents which are built using providers as is the case with
			the UNIX agents and some of the database agents. It can be defined at any level in the
			monitoring session.</listitem>
			<listitem>Multi-host heterogeneous data view: this option is only available for data views
			defined at monitoring session level (the first node in the tree). Used to build views that
			requires counters from different entities not necessarily related, accross multiple hosts. The
			hosts are selected using a regular expression.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		</para>

		<para>The following figure shows the last page of the wizard that creates a homogeneous data view
			defining a bar chart with CPU usage	for all processes on a windows host. The chart uses
			a stacked renderer for privileged and user time. A reaction is also defined which will
			be triggered if the sum of privileged and user time for a process is greater than 90 for
			a one minute interval.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>View wizard</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/view_wizard_1.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>This is a description of each column in the 'Counters' table (even so the example is
		given for a homogeneous data view they keep their meaning for all other types):
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Use: select this to choose counters that will be used in the view.</listitem>
			<listitem>Counter: not editable; shows the name of the counter.</listitem>
			<listitem>Id: a generated id for each counter; for the selected counters the generated
			values have been changed to make them more readable as they have been used in the
			definition of the function.</listitem>
			<listitem>IName: the instance name for the selected resource; usually the value generated
			by the wizard doesn't have to be changed.</listitem>
			<listitem>Name: the name for the selected resource; usually the value generated
			by the wizard doesn't have to be changed.</listitem>
			<listitem>Description: the description associated with the respective counter; if left
			empty, the description of the counter will be used.</listitem>
			<listitem>Max: the maximum value of that counter; used by the renderer to set the
			initial size of the value range; if left empty the value range will be resized dynamically.</listitem>
			<listitem>Min: the minimum value of that counter; used as a hint for the renderer.</listitem>
			<listitem>Code: is the same as the 'code' style for resources; a piece of java code that
			takes as a parameter the value of the counter and returns a value of the same type. Used
			mainly to make quick conversions without defining a function. For instance the code to change the
			value of a counter from bytes to megabytes would be like this: 'return id/Math.pow(2,20);'
			where the id is the Id of the counter.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>dashboard editor</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraDashboardEditor">
		<title>Dashboard Editor</title>

		<para>For easy access to a full system overview, multiple views can be grouped
		and plotted together. To bring up this editor, select the Dashboards tab of
		an entity, right-click and choose 'Add'.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Dashboard Editor</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/dashboard_editor.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>The left panel shows the same monitoring session tree and the right one
		shows views and counters for the selected entity. These can be added to the bottom
		panel which shows the contents of the dashboard.</para>

	</sect2>
	<para></para>
	<para></para>

</section>
