<section id="secFAQ">
	<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

	<qandaset>

	<qandaentry>
		<question><para>How can I easily monitor the availability of several web sites?</para></question>
		<answer><para>Add the host names of all web sites to the monitoring session (right click on 
		the session node and 'Add Host(s)'; then select all hosts in the tree, right click and select
		'Add Agent(s)'; from the list of available agents select 'Service Availablility'; in the configuration
		panel enter for 'Data' the value 'GET /' or 'GET /<page_name>' FOLLOWED BY A BLANK LINE; 
		for the 'Port' property enter the port where your web server if configured to listen and press
		'Activate Agent'. From the list of views available for the session node enable then plot the one
		called 'TCP/IP services availability overview'. After you start your monitoring session the view
		will contain a table with the critical counters; if you want to add more agents just activate 
		them and this view will be automatically updated.
		</para></answer>
	</qandaentry>
	
	<qandaentry>
		<question><para>How do I disable reactions?</para></question>
		<answer><para>Reactions can be disabled from the 'Actions\Disable Reactions' menu.</para></answer>
	</qandaentry>	
	
	<qandaentry>
		<question><para>How do I create jobs that execute Windows command line instructions?</para></question>
		<answer><para>
		Instead of invoking a command like 'del' directly you will have to prefix it with cmd.exe /C like
		in the example below</para>
		<programlisting role="linespecific">cmd.exe /C del /Q C:\temp\logs\*</programlisting>
		</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
		<question><para>How do I create my own agent package?</para></question>
		<answer><para>If you created you own custom agent (see <xref linkend="secCustomData#paraAgentInstaller"/>) 
		and you want to distribute it you can create your own agent package by using the Export facility.</para>
		</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
		<question><para>How do I copy values from a table control?</para></question>
		<answer><para>Double click on the cell, select content (press Ctrl+A) and copy (Ctrl+C or using the context menu)</para>
		</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	</qandaset>

</section>
