<section id="secCustomData">
	<title>Monitoring Custom Data</title>

	<para>Another exciting feature of &programName; is the ability to add custom
	data sources and to integrate them seamlessly with the built-in agents.</para>

   <para>A Provider is the component which collects data from an external source
   and converts it into Entities and Counters. Providers are always associated
   with Agents, from which they inherit configuration options, and to which they
   contribute Counters.</para>

   <para>The steps involved in creating a custom data source are:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>Create an Agent (optional). Using Agent Installer create a new custom agent which
      will host the new Provider(s). The agent will provide configuration common
      to all its providers, and will serve as a root for the entity tree.</listitem>

      <listitem>Create a Provider for this Agent. Using Provider Manager, select the new
      Agent (or an existing one) and add a new Provider for it. Select one of provider
      types (Java, SQL or Process) and configure its running parameters and the structure
      of its Entities and Counters.</listitem>

      <listitem>Activate the new Agent as you would any other agent, optionally enabling
      or disabling some providers.</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<indexterm><primary>Agent installer</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraAgentInstaller">
		<title>Agent Installer</title>

      <para>This window is accessible from Tools/Agent Installer. To add a new Agent,
      click Install and select a configuration template (SQL, Java or Process). This will
      populate the fields with appropriate values, and will be enough for most uses.
      Here is a reference of the agent's properties, some of them are intended for future
      advanced customizations:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
		   <listitem>Name: agent name, cannot be changed after creation.</listitem>
		   <listitem>Description: agent description.</listitem>
		   <listitem>Class: Java class containing agent implementation, manual editing not
         recommended, reserved for future use.</listitem>
         <listitem>Category: The name of the category which the agent belongs to. The predefined
         values are the following:
        	<itemizedlist>
		   		<listitem>applications</listitem>
		   		<listitem>network</listitem>
		   		<listitem>databases</listitem>
		   		<listitem>webServers</listitem>
		   		<listitem>appServers</listitem>
		   		<listitem>operatingSystems</listitem>
		   		<listitem>miscellaneous</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
		   <listitem>Message Catalog: Usually the same as agent name, the name of properties
         file (located under config/messages), if any, containing message translations.</listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>The following agent definition data can be assigned to one or more agent versions:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
		   <listitem>System Versions: Whether agent can monitor multiple versions of the
         same system. Providers can be associated to one or more versions defined here.</listitem>
		   <listitem>Location: Whether the agent will be executed locally or deployed remotely.</listitem>
		   <listitem>Levels: Whether agent supports multiple monitoring levels, and which
         is the default.</listitem>
		   <listitem>Jar Paths: List of external jar files that agent may require.</listitem>
		   <listitem>UI Jar: jar containing agent's user interface (configuration panel).</listitem>
		   <listitem>Config Panel: Java class containing implementation of the configuration
         panel displayed in 'Activate Agent' window. If one of the agent templates has been chosen before
         this field will already be populated.</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>

		<figure>
			<title>Agent Installer</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/agent_installer.png"/>
		</figure>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>providers</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraProviders">
		<title>Providers</title>

      <para>Access this window from Tools/Provider Manager. To create a Provider, first
      select an Agent and click Add. This will bring up Provider Instance Editor.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Provider Instsance Editor</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/provider_editor.png"/>
		</figure>

      <para>Common fields:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>Agent Versions: available if the associated agent has defined
         a list of versions. Select which versions this provider is intended to
         work with.</listitem>

         <listitem>Provider Instance Name: Name for this provider</listitem>

         <listitem>Provider Instance Description: Description for this provider</listitem>

         <listitem>Type: Select either SQL, Java or Process from the dropdown list.
         Different provider types will have different configuration options,
         detailed below.</listitem>

         <listitem>Location: Run this provider localy (on the machine where
         &programName; console is running), remotely (on the monitored host) or
         wherever the agent is configured to run (inherit location).</listitem>

         <listitem>Optional: Provider can be enabled/disabled before agent is
         activated.</listitem>

         <listitem>Selected: The default enabled/disabled state of the provider.</listitem>

         <listitem>Requires private collector: Check this if the provider may
         occasionaly take much longer to execute. If this is selected the provider
         will not affect the functioning of the common data collectors. Be selective when
         enabling this flag as too many collectors will impact overall system performance.</listitem>

	   </itemizedlist>

      <para>Note that in all options detailed below you can use properties of the
      agent, through the following syntax: {agent.propertyname}. Thus, if the agent's
      configuration has a property called 'propertyname', its value will be used here.
      This makes it convenient for example to attach multiple SQL based providers,
      which will all use the username and password configured in the agent.</para>

      <para>Along with the {agent.propertyname} syntax, the following built-in tokens
      can be used:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>{agent} : converts at runtime to agent's name.</listitem>
	<listitem>{host} : converts to name of the host that this agent is deployed on.</listitem>
	<listitem>{home} : converts to the folder where &programName; is installed.</listitem>
	<listitem>{tick} : converts to the sampling interval configured for the agents in seconds.</listitem>
	<listitem>{tick.ms} : converts to the same sampling interval, but given in
	milliseconds.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

	  <indexterm><primary>Java provider</primary><secondary>options</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>Java specific options:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>Classpath: Java classpath required by implementation class.</listitem>
         <listitem>Class loader id: The id of the class loader to use; Use the
         same id for multiple provider instances using the same code to allow
         sharing of resources.</listitem>
         <listitem>Implementation class: The name of the java class with the
         implementation for this provider.</listitem>
         <listitem>Implementation class parameters: Parameters list to be passed
         to the impplementation class. Each parameter must be between double
         quotes (e.g. "param1" "param2").</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>

	   For more information on Java providers see <xref linkend="secProvidersJava"/>.

	  <indexterm><primary>Process provider</primary><secondary>options</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>Process specific options:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>Command: Command line to execute.</listitem>
         <listitem>Process is volatile: Check this if the process returns a block
         of information and then exits. &programName; will execute the command
         line each time it needs to retrieve data. Leave this unchecked if the
         process is continuously returning data.</listitem>
         <listitem>End of buffer regex: Regular expression that marks a line as being the end of a data buffer.
         If a process is not volatile and this parameter is left empty every line of output
         will be sent to the data parser otherwise lines will be buffered until a line where this
         regular expression has a match is found.</listitem>
         <listitem>Process remote execution mode: Set to one of the following values:
			 <itemizedlist>
	    	     <listitem>{agent.executionMode}: The provider will inherit the execution mode
	    	     from the agent configuration.</listitem>
	    	     <listitem>Normal: The provider will be executed locally on the Console host.</listitem>
  	    	     <listitem>Telnet: The provider will be executed using a Telnet session on the
  	    	     monitored host.</listitem>
  	    	     <listitem>SSH2: The provider will be executed using a secure shell session on the
  	    	     monitored host.</listitem>
	         </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>Username: Only applies for 'Telnet' or 'SSH2' execution modes: it is the
         username used to connect to the monitored host. The default value is {agent.Username} which
         allows the provider the use the value defined at agent level.</listitem>
         <listitem>Password: applies for 'Telnet' or 'SSH2' execution modes: it is the password
         used to connect to the monitored host. The default value is {agent.Password} which allows the provider the use
         the value defined at agent level.</listitem>
         <listitem>Shell prompt: applies for the 'Telnet' execution mode: it is the shell prompt for
         the telnet session. To find out this value log in first through a telnet terminal and using the username that you intend to use for the
         'Username' parameter: The default value is {agent.ShellPrompt} which allows the provider the use
         the value defined at agent level</listitem>
         <listitem>Connection port: applies for 'Telnet' or 'SSH2' execution modes: it is
         the port used for the remote connection. The default value is {agent.Port} which allows
         the provider the use the value defined at agent level</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>

	  <indexterm><primary>SQL provider</primary><secondary>options</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>SQL specific options:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>Classpath: Classpath pointing to the JDBC driver code.</listitem>
         <listitem>Class loader id: The id of the class loader to use; Use the same id
         for multiple provider instances using the same code to allow sharing of
         resources.</listitem>
         <listitem>JDBC driver class: The name of the JDBC driver class.</listitem>
         <listitem>Username: Authenticate using this username.</listitem>
         <listitem>Password: Authenticate using this password.</listitem>
         <listitem>JDBC connection string: Connection string used to establish
         the database connection.</listitem>
         <listitem>SQL query: The SQL query to execute for data collection.</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>

		For more information on SQL providers see <xref linkend="secProvidersSQL"/>.

	  <indexterm><primary>Table parser</primary></indexterm>
      <para>Table parser options:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
	     <listitem>Convert column to row: If set to true converts the single column result of a query
         into a single row table; used to facilitate the use of a
         table parser instead of a properties parser(see the example below); by doing this
         one can group the data into a hierarchy of entities which would not be possible using
         the properties parser on this type of data</listitem>

         <listitem>Column separator: character(s) separating columns. Default
         is whitespace.</listitem>

         <listitem>Ignore lines matching: Each line of text will be search for this regular expression.
         A line containing it will be ignored by parser.</listitem>

         <listitem>Ignore data columns at: Use this to handle the situation where missing values for a cell
         can be the same as the column separator. This will allow you to ignore extra cells in
         rows of data.</listitem>

         <listitem>Accumulate volatile entities: if selected, entities generated
         dynamically (for example the list of processes on a system) will persist
         in the entity tree. If not selected dynamic entities will appear and
         dissapear as they are found or not in the data source.</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>

	   <para>Convert column to row example:
	   If input data is:
   		<programlisting role="linespecific">
		 10
		 22
		 4
		 5
		 506
		 269
		</programlisting>
	   	then by using the conversion the output will be:
   		<programlisting role="linespecific">
		 10 22 4 5 506 269
		</programlisting>
	   which can be now extracted into a hierarchy like this:
   		<programlisting role="linespecific">
   		root
   		 |_Networking (with counters Aborted_clients and Aborted_connects)
   		   |_Traffic (with counters Bytes_received	Bytes_sent)
   		 |_Binlog (with counters Binlog_cache_disk_use Binlog_cache_use
		</programlisting>
	   </para>

	  <indexterm><primary>Properties parser</primary></indexterm>
      <para>Properties parser options:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>Entity regex: A regular expression used to extract entity names. The
         regex must contain one capturing group. All matches of this group will generate an
         entity, which gets added under the Base entity (see the note below).</listitem>

         <listitem>Property/Value regex: A regular expression to extract name/value pairs.
         The regex must contain two capturing groups. By default matches for the first group
         will generate values, and matches for the second group will generate counter names.</listitem>

         <listitem>Value is second group: For the regex above, specifies whether the second
         group will generate values and the first will generate counter names.</listitem>

         <listitem>Base entity: All entities generated dynamically will be added under this
         base entity.</listitem>

         <listitem>Ignore lines matching: Each line of text will be search for this regular expression.
         A line containing it will be ignored by parser.</listitem>

         <listitem>Accumulate volatile entities: if selected, entities generated
         dynamically (for example the list of processes on a system) will persist
         in the entity tree. If not selected dynamic entities will appear and
         dissapear as they are found or not in the data source.</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>
	   <para>NOTE: Each counter resulted from parsing will need to have an entry in the list of
	   counters, with a counter ID and an entity ID matching the ones extracted from text. If
	   the regular expressions match values which are not in this list they will be ignored,
	   without creating new counters or entities.</para>

	   <para>Example of a property parser definition:</para>
<programlisting role="linespecific">
For the command:
#netstat -s
Ip:
    1916 total packets received
    0 forwarded
    0 incoming packets discarded
    1696 incoming packets delivered
    1718 requests sent out
Icmp:
    0 ICMP messages received
    0 input ICMP message failed.
    ICMP input histogram:
    0 ICMP messages sent
    0 ICMP messages failed
    ICMP output histogram:


The parser definition is:
Entity regex: ([^:].*):
Property/Value regex: \s*([^\s]+)\s*([^\(]+).*
Base entity: root/Network protocols

And the generated entities are:
Network protocols
   +- Ip
   |    [total packets received]
   |    [forwarded]
   |    [incoming packets discarded]
   |    [incoming packets delivered]
   |    [requests sent out]
   +- Icmp
        [ICMP messages received]
        [input ICMP message failed]
        [ICMP messages sent]
        [ICMP messages failed]

</programlisting>


	  <para>Column definition</para>
      <para>Column definition is the main part of creating a provider. Each of
      the three provider types (SQL, Java and Process) will output a table. On
      this Parser page you are giving a meaning to each column of this table,
      by associating it with an Entity or Counter.</para>

      <para>The parser needs to have definitions for all columns, regardless
      whether they will be visible in the entity tree or not. To skip a column,
      leave the EntityID and CounterID empty for that particular column index.</para>

      <para>To convert a column into a Counter, enter a CounterID and an EntityID for it.
      The CounterID is a simple text, which will be looked up in the agent's Message Catalog
      (see <xref linkend="paraAgentInstaller"/>). If no translation is available
      for that text, the CounterID will be displayed as-is throughout &programName;.</para>

      <para>The syntax of an EntityID is: <programlisting role="linespecific">root/e1/e2/...</programlisting>
      where e1, e2 and so on are simple strings, localised in the same way as the
      CounterID. Each of these elements will result in an Entity being added to the
      tree. The final Entity in the path will contain the Counter.</para>

      <para>To convert a column into an Entity, only enter an EntityID, but no CounterID.</para>

      <para>To create dynamic (volatile) entities based on values in a certain column,
      use the syntax: <programlisting role="linespecific">root/e1/{n}</programlisting>
      where n is the index of the column containing entity names.</para>

      <para>An example of creating entities and counters out of the output of
      the Unix command ps:</para>
<programlisting role="linespecific">
# ps
   PID  CLS PRI TTY      TIME COMD
  5996   TS  70 pts004   0:00 sh
 18294   TS  59 pts004   0:00 ps
</programlisting>

      <para>Parser definitions would be:</para>
<programlisting role="linespecific">
Column     EntityID              CounterID
0       root/Processes/{0}
1       root/Processes/{0}       Scheduling class
2       root/Processes/{0}       Priority
3       root/Processes/{0}       TTY
4       root/Processes/{0}       Time
5       root/Processes/{0}       Command line
</programlisting>

      <para>And when the agent containing this provider is activated, the entity
      tree would look like:</para>
<programlisting role="linespecific">
Agent
  +- Processes
      +- 5996
      |   [Scheduling class]
      |   [Priority]
      |   [TTY]
      |   [Time]
      |   [Command line]
      +- 18294
          [Scheduling class]
          [Priority]
          [TTY]
          [Time]
          [Command line]
</programlisting>

      <para>You can find more complex examples in the definitions of some
      &programName;'s own agents, such as Linux or Oracle.</para>

      <para>The Descriptors tab allows entering descriptions and types for
      entities and counters:</para>
	   <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>Description (for both entities and counters): simple string which
         can be translated, or displayed as is.</listitem>

         <listitem>Type: choose double, long or string for this counter, which
         will affect how it is displayed in charts.</listitem>

         <listitem>Discrete: check if this counter does not have continuous values
         (for example it's an error code), may affect the way it is displayed in some
         charts.</listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>

</section>
