<section id="secPerfMon">
	<title>Performance Monitoring</title>

	<indexterm><primary>session</primary><secondary>agent</secondary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraAddingHosts">
		<title>Adding Hosts</title>
		<para>In order to start monitoring you must first create a <xref linkend="paraMonitoringSession"/>
		by clicking on the New Session button. This will prompt you for an initial list of
		hosts (more can be added later on by right-clicking on the session and selecting 'Add Host').
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Add Host(s)</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/add_hosts.png"/>
		</figure>
		<para>This window accepts a space-separated list of either host names or IP addresses.
		Each item in the list will be added to the monitoring session, and &programName; will
		attempt to connect to each one individually. &programName; accepts that machines can
		go in or out of a performance network, therefore it is not an error to be unable to
		connect to a host.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Session Hosts</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/session_hosts.png"/>
		</figure>

		<para>A host can have two possible 'online/offline' states, as follows</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>HM:'online/offline' shows whether <xref linkend="paraHostManager"/> is running on this machine.</listitem>
			<listitem>P:'online/offline' shows whether this machine responds to ICMP ping messages.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="paraAddingAgents">
		<title>Adding Agents</title>
		<para>Once at least one host is added to the monitoring session, agents can be
		activated by right-clicking the host and selecting 'Add Agent(s)' context menu item.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Agent Activator</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/agent_activator.png"/>
			<para>Select location as either 'remote' or 'local', as described in
				<xref linkend="paraAgents"/>. For agents which require this, also
				select the particular version of monitored application.</para>
		</figure>
		<para>See <xref linkend="chAgents"/> for a list of agents supported by the current version
		of &programName; and the list of configurable parameters for each one.</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>plotting</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraPlotting">
		<title>Plotting</title>

		<para>Graphic controls in &programName; are displayed on boards, with each board
		supporting one type of control. See <xref linkend="secControls"/> for more details
		on available controls.</para>

      <para>To plot, select one or more counters, right click and select Plot from the
      context menu.</para>

		<para>Depending on the type of item plotted, a different graphic will be created.
		However in each case all resulting controls will always be placed on their appropriate
		board.
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Numeric Counter: If the value of the counter being plotted is a number, it will be
			displayed as a time series on an appropiate <xref linkend="paraChartControl"/></listitem>
			<listitem>Text Counter: If the counter has a text value then a <xref linkend="paraPropertiesControl"/>
			is created.</listitem>
			<listitem>View: The control created is specified by the view's definition.</listitem>
			<listitem>Dashboard: A set of controls are created as specified by the dashboard
			definition.</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		Note that certain types of counters are plotted on specialized view boards; for example the 'Log Records'
		counter of the <xref linkend="secLogFile"/> agent is always plotted on its dedicated 'Log Board'.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>session</primary><secondary>running</secondary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraSessionRunning">
		<title>Running the Monitoring Session</title>

		<para>Clicking the 'Run Session' button will instruct all agents to start collecting
		information, and will start populating screen controls. Data will arrive periodically
		with a frequency given by the current <xref linkend="paraSamplingInterval"/>.</para>

		<para>Changing the session-level sampling interval will immediately be applied
		to all agents which don't override this value.</para>

		<para>If logging is enabled (see <xref linkend="secLogging"/>) then all information
		received from the agents is saved in the chosen log file. Logging can be enabled
		and disabled while a monitoring session is running.</para>

		<para>Clicking the 'Stop Session' button will stop all data collection and logging.
		A session can be stopped and restarted any number of times.</para>

		<para>A session can be saved into / loaded from a session file. The following items
		will be persisted:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>the list of hosts</listitem>
			<listitem>the list of agents and their configuration</listitem>
			<listitem>all enabled counters, views and dashboards</listitem>
			<listitem>screen elements, including controls, dashboards and data view screens.</listitem>
			<listitem>session related configuration, eg. sampling interval</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>

</section>
