<section id="secJobs">
	<title>Jobs</title>

	<para>&programName; provides ways to schedule and run jobs. It is provided mainly to be used
	 as a delivery mechanism for reaction rules (see <xref linkend="secReactions"/>).
	 In order to do that jobs must be created in the Job Library and their name will be used
	 as a parameter in the reaction definition.
	 In the current version just two type of jobs are provided:

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>Command - which requires the HostManager to be running on the remote host.</listitem>
		<listitem>Telnet command - which is executed via a telnet session.</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	 It is possible to define jobs that will run on multiple hosts by using regular expressions
	 when specifying the host name in the job definition. In order for the name of the host to be
	 treated as a regular expression it has to be surrounded by paranthesis like in the following expamle:
	 (host*) to define a job to be run on all hosts matching the pattern host*
	 </para>

	<indexterm><primary>jobs</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>library</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraSchedulingJobs">
		<title>Scheduling Jobs</title>
		<para>Open the Job Manager which is accessible from the 'Tools\Job Manager' menu and
		click on the Schedule Job button; this opens the Job Editor dialog.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Job editor</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/job_editor.png"/>
		</figure>

		When you are finished press the Ok button and the job should now be visible in the Job Manager.
		Once the job has been executed the content of its output and error streams are available in the
		'Ouptput' and 'Error' panels of the Job Manager.

		<figure>
			<title>Job editor</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/job_manager.png"/>
		</figure>

	</sect2>

	<indexterm><primary>jobs</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>library</primary></indexterm>
	<sect2 id="paraCreatingJobs">
		<title>Creating Jobs for the Job Library</title>
		<para>Open the Job Manager which is accessible from the 'Tools\Job Manager' menu and
		click on the Job Library button; this opens the dialog which allows you to maintain jobs
		stored in the library; then click on the 'Add' button to open the Job Editor.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Library job editor</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/job_lib_editor.png"/>
		</figure>
	</sect2>

	<para></para>
	<para></para>

</section>
